Guide to the Henry Onderdonk papers ARC.045
Brooklyn Historical Society
- Series 2: Correspondence, 1835-1885
  As described in the Arrangement Note, the series has four sets of correspondence. These sets are more a reflection of Onderdonk's filing systems, Brooklyn Historical Society's past processing practices, and the varied sources of the correspondence than of any substantial difference in content or chronology. Accordingly, the general themes of the correspondence are consistent across the sets, and many of the correspondents are found in more than one set. Nonetheless, each set has its own strengths:
  A principal theme of Sub-series 2.1 is the Revolutionary War, especially the Battle of Long Island and, to a lesser extent, the execution of Nathan Hale. The set also includes notes on genealogy, acknowledgements of receipts of Onderdonk's published works by individuals, libraries, and others; invitations to readings, college commencements, celebrations, meetings, and more; and requests of Onderdonk for historical and family history. Much of the correspondence takes the form of responses to specific Onderdonk requests for information, publications, and so forth. The bound correspondence includes some transcriptions of Long Island town records, including those of Jamaica, Flushing, and Hempstead. Hempstead history is a notable subject of the bound correspondence. Substantive correspondence in the set comes from authors and historians James Fenimore Cooper, George Bancroft, Charles Hoadly, Jared Sparks, Lorenzo Sabine, Thomas A. Strong, Benjamin F. Thompson, I.W. Stuart, and E.B. O'Callaghan. Other notable correspondents, though not necessarily conveying substantive matter, include John Breckinridge, James Buchanan, Washington Irving, William H. Seward, and Hamilton Fish, along with other U.S. senators, Congressmen, and state politicians. Correspondents that appear in other CBH collections include Henry Stiles, Henry Pierrepont, Jeremiah Johnson, and Henry Murphy.
  Sub-series 2.2 also principally involves genealogy, requests for information, sharing information about the availability of particular books, and the like. The set includes a folder of correspondence with or about Quakers (Friends). Most notable in this regard is a letter from Rachel Hicks discussing Elias Hicks and Gideon Seaman, along with Quakers on Long Island in relation to American Indians, slavery, and the American Revolution. Also included in this set is correspondence from Onderdonk's former classmates at Harvard College and other Boston-area correspondents. Notable correspondents in this set include Lyman Draper commenting on the State Historical Society of Wisconsin, historian Jeptha Root Simms and Columbia College librarian William Alfred Jones commenting on various historical works or events, and Long Island genealogist Benjamin D. Hicks. Onderdonk's indices and lists of names for this set are filed at the front of each folder.
  Sub-series 2.3 includes requests of Onderdonk for information, publications, etc., and responses to Onderdonk's requests for same. The principal subject matter concerns genealogy, church history (especially Quakers and the Episcopal Church), and the American Revolution. Major correspondents include historians and genealogists Teunis Bergen, Jacob T. Bowne, Rev. Edward T. Corwin of Millstone, NJ, John J. Latting, and E.B. O'Callaghan. Other correspondents that can be found in CBH collections include Henry C. Murphy, Henry Stiles, and William S. Pelletreau. Requests for publications included correspondence from US senators and Congressmen, such as Roscoe Conkling, Hamilton Fish, and Dwight Townsend. A letter from William Pelletreau in the "various correspondents" folders referring to four beads of wampum may provide insight to the source of the wampum found in Series 1. An 1875 letter from William Potts of Camden, NJ, surveys Quaker objections to slavery in New Jersey and Pennsylvania.
  Sub-series 2.4 includes an 1856 letter from future president James Buchanan acknowledging his induction to the Long Island Bible Society, James Fenimore Cooper writing of British general Oliver de Lancey, E.F. Ellet corresponding with Onderdonk concerning her histories of the American Revolution (which emphasized women and domestic matters), and Gideon Frost, John Hicks, Benson Lossing, and James Riker on sources and writings concerning Long Island Quakers and Revolutionary War history.
  - Sub-Series 2.1: "Historical letters addressed to Henry Onderdonk, Jr.", 1835-1869
    - Supplementary guide to correspondence in Sub-Series 2.1 (Box 5, Folder 2)
    - "Historical letters," first series, 1835-1869; 1974.019 (Box 5, Folder 3-27)
    - "Historical Letters," second series, 1838-1869; 1974.020 (Box 5, Folder 28)
  - Sub-Series 2.2: Letters indexed by correspondent, 1840-1889 (Box 5, Folder 29, Box 6, Folder 1-3)
  - Sub-Series 2.3: Research requests, 1842-1885; 1978.088 (Box 6, Folder 4-18, Box 7, Folder 1-6)
  - Sub-Series 2.4: Correspondence by correspondent, 1844-1885 (Box 7, Folder 7-24)
    This set includes a list, circa 1878, of correspondents included in letters sent by Onderdonk to Brooklyn Historical Society.
- Series 3: Subject files, 1729-1895
  The series is arranged by subject.
  This series includes a variety of original historical documents such as handbills, petitions, fliers, programs, and financial records related to various Long Island communities. Queens County is especially well-represented in the series, including various original invoices for expenses related to the transportation, maintenance, and execution of prisoners in Queens County; electoral campaign materials for temperance candidate Simon Craft (1846), advertisements for James M. Huntting's English and Classical Family School (1857), a share of stock in the Jamaica Circulating Library (1861), and other matter. Documents related to Union Hall Academy of Jamaica include student petitions, a list of students (1847), an advertisement with tuition rates, rules and other information, and student exhibition programs. For present-day Nassau County, documents include the program for the laying of the cornerstone at the Cathedral of the Incarnation in Garden City (1877), a Hempstead Seminary advertisement (1837), notices for public celebratory events at Little Neck (1857) and Manhasset (1872), and a 1793 document dividing land (likely at Cow Neck) between James Hewlett and George Rapelje. The series includes genealogical research notes and correspondence for the Dodge family of Long Island, a transcription of a French and Indian War era (1758) muster roll and related notes concerning a New York battalion from a regiment commanded by Col. Oliver de Lancey, and an account from a doctor's daybook showing services rendered (1729-1731).
  - Union Hall Academy, 1829-1871 (Box 7, Folder 25)
    The Union Hall Academy materials include one folder of loose items and one bound volume in its own housing.
  - Dodge Family genealogical notes, 1878-1879 (Box 7, Folder 26)
  - French and Indian War, 1758; 1977.131 (Box 7, Folder 27)
  - Queens County, 1791-1861 (Box 7, Folder 28)
  - Queens County - prisoner expenses, 1783-1785 (Box 7, Folder 29)
  - Long Island, 1837-1872 (Box 7, Folder 30)
  - Long Island - churches, 1833-1881 (Box 7, Folder 31)
  - Notes, clippings, and ephemera, 1729-1895 (Box 7, Folder 32, Box 11)
    Includes a 1798 announcement of Robert Livingston's nomination for Governor, an 1895 notice of the sale of Virginia State Library reports, and an 1870 address from Henry A. Reeves, among other items. Two oversize items were removed to a larger box: "A Story of Olden Times" from Ballou's Pictorial Drawing-Room Companion, circa 1855, and the 1729-1730 doctor's daybook account mentioned in the Scope and Contents note of this series.
- Series 4: Scrapbooks, circa 1788-1882
  A seven volume set of scrapbooks Onderdonk finished compiling in 1869 concerning Queens County is first in the series, followed by an 1864 volume with material covering all three Long Island counties of the time (Kings, Queens, Suffolk).
  The date range used in the container list is the approximate date of the original documents in the scrapbooks. Some of the scrapbook documents, particularly in Queens County Volume 1, are mid-nineteenth century transcriptions, newspaper reprints of old items of interest such as town record entries, historical narratives published in newspapers, or other forms of secondary material concerning the seventeenth century and later; accordingly, a second date range, found within the item description, is used for the approximate date range of the historical period referred to by the content of the scrapbook documents.
  The content of the seven volume Queens County set advances in chronological order, covering historical matters from circa 1663 to 1868. Much of the material concerning the period until the 1820s are not contemporary documents; the earliest contemporary documents date from circa 1798. Several of the volumes include post-1868 handbills and other ephemera (i.e., material dating from after Onderdonk's completion of the scrapbooks) tipped-in to the scrapbooks at various places in no discernible order. The content of the earliest volumes in the set seem to adhere to a less rigorous organization than the later volumes which run in a reliable chronological order.
  The content of the one volume scrapbook includes well-defined sections on Kings, Queens, and Suffolk counties. The volume includes a subject index prepared by Onderdonk. There is also a partial list of contents at the front of the scrapbook prepared by a Brooklyn Historical Society librarian in 1940.
  This series includes eight scrapbooks compiled by Onderdonk in the 1860s. Seven of these scrapbooks, completed in 1869, comprise a set covering Queens County, which at the time also included the towns that would later become Nassau County. In these volumes, Jamaica, Flushing, and Hempstead are perhaps most prominent, but other locales, including Newtown, Oyster Bay, Cow Neck, Roslyn, and Glen Cove, are represented significantly. Occasional Kings County material appears, though not extensively; generally this material especially concerns Brooklyn and are often clippings from a series of historical pieces published by the Eagle. The bulk of the material consists of newspaper clippings; it is seldom clear which newspapers were the source of particular clippings, but at least three newspapers appear to have been significant sources: Democrat (Jamaica); Long Island Star; and Long Island Farmer and Queens County Advertiser. Some handbills, advertisements, circulars, and other such ephemera can also be found in the scrapbooks; in most instances, these items date from after the scrapbooks compilation date and are tipped-in at seemingly random places, such as a circa 1880 Manhattan Beach Railway timetable and map found in Volume 2.
  The clippings focus on Queens County matters of potential local historical interest, so broader New York or national events are not represented aside from their local connection, nor are literary or other fictional writings included. The subject matter of the clippings is wide-ranging, but there is also a high level of consistency across the seven volumes for several subjects. These subjects include political matters, such as accounts of political gatherings, detailed results by town of presidential, state, and local elections, and party positions; agriculture, such as agricultural society fairs (especially the Queens County Agricultural Society) and lists of premiums awarded by the societies; temperance and temperance societies; government matters, such as accounts of town meetings, meetings of town trustees or supervisors, and court proceedings; announcements, public notices and advertisements, such as those for public auctions, lectures to be given, openings and other events at schools, churches, and other institutions, camp meetings, stagecoach departure schedules, and recreational outings and events; financial information, such as taxpayer lists and assessments, town finances, and corporate operations; crimes (e.g., murder, rape, assault, theft) and accidental deaths (e.g., drownings, fires, falls); lists of interments; July 4 celebrations, including accounts of the toasts given; and railroad development and reports of operations. References to African-Americans, though not frequent, appear throughout the volumes in the context of the above subjects, such as runaway notices (Vol. 1), announcements of camp meetings (e.g., Vol. 4) or annual beach parties (Vol. 6 and 7), and in accounts of crimes, accidents or deaths.
  The first volume includes Revolutionary War events, including information on the prison ships and the refugees from Long Island. Volumes 6 and 7 include much on the Civil War as it relates to Queens County, such as town war meetings, lists of draftees, deaths, and regiment recruitment, musters, and other activities. Items with an obvious personal connection to Onderdonk are common, including material on Union Hall Academy and articles referring to individuals with the Onderdonk name. By 1866, the scrapbooks include box scores and summaries of local baseball games. The eighth scrapbook in the series was compiled at an earlier date, in 1864, than the seven volume set. The single volume includes Kings and Suffolk counties in its scope, as well as Queens County. The subject matter of this one volume is generally consistent with that described above. Because of the overlap in chronology, the Queens County section of this scrapbook can be viewed as a supplement to the seven volume set. The Kings County section of this scrapbook consists principally of a series of historical narratives published by the Brooklyn Eagle circa 1862.
  Some of these scrapbooks are in fragile condition, as noted at the file level, and their use is restricted.
  - Queens County Volume 1 (1663-1829), circa 1798-1880 (Box 8)
    Use of this scrapbook is restricted due to its fragile condition.
  - Queens County Volume 2 (1830-1836), circa 1830-1881 (Box 9)
  - Queens County Volume 3 (1837-1843), circa 1837-1880 (Box 9)
  - Queens County Volume 4 (1844-1849), circa 1844-1877 (Box 9)
  - Queens County Volume 5 (1849-1856), circa 1849-1856 (Box 10)
  - Queens County Volume 6 (1855-1864), circa 1855-1864 (Box 11)
  - Queens County Volume 7 (1864-1868), circa 1864-1868 (Box 10)
  - Kings, Queens and Suffolk Counties (circa 1640-1882), circa 1788-1882 (Box 8)